chapter 6.
About this time an ambitious young reporter from New York arrived one
morning at Gatsby’s door and asked him if he had anything to say.
“Anything to say about what?” inquired Gatsby politely.
“Why— —any statement to give out.” It transpired after a confused five
minutes that the man had heard Gatsby’s name around his office in a connection
which he either wouldn’t reveal or didn’t fully understand. This was his day
off and with laudable initiative he had hurried out “to see.”
It was a random shot, and yet the reporter’s instinct was right.
Gatsby’s notoriety, spread about by the hundreds who had accepted his
hospitality and so become authorities on his past, had increased all summer until
he fell just short of being news.
Contemporary legends such as the “underground pipeline to Canada” attached
themselves to him, and there was one persistent story that he didn’t live in
a house at all, but in a boat that looked like a house and was moved secretly up
and down the Long Island shore. Just why these inventions were a source of
satisfaction to James Gatz of North Dakota, isn’t easy to say. James Gatz—
—that was really, or at least legally, his name.
He had changed it at the age of 17 and at the specific moment that witnessed
the beginning of his career— —when he saw Dan Cody’s yacht drop anchor over the
most insidious flat on Lake Superior. It was James Gatz who had been loafing
along the beach that afternoon in a torn green jersey and a pair of canvas pants,
but it was already Jay Gatsby who borrowed a rowboat, pulled out to the
Ptolemy and informed Cody that a wind might catch him and break him up in half
an hour. I suppose he’d had the name ready for a long time, even then. His
parents were shiftless and unsuccessful farm people— —his imagination had never
really accepted them as his parents at all.
The truth was that Jay Gatsby of West Egg, Long Island, sprang from his Platonic
conception of himself.
He was the son of God— —a phrase which, if it means anything, means just that— —and he
must be about His Father’s business, the service of a vast, vulgar, and meritricious beauty.
So he invented just the sort of Jay Gatsby that a 17 year old boy would be
likely to invent, and to this conception he was faithful to the end.
For over a year he had been beating his way along the south shore of Lake
Superior as a Clam Digger and a salmon Fisher or in any other capacity that
brought him food and bed. His brown, hardening body lived naturally through
the hard Fierce half-lazy work of the bracing days.
He knew women early, and since they spoiled him he became contemptuous of
them, of young virgins because they were ignorant, of the others because they were
hysterical about things which in his overwhelming self-absorption he took for granted.
But his heart was in a constant, turbulent riot. The most grotesque and
fantastic conceits haunted him in his bed at night. A universe of ineffable
gaudiness spun itself out in his brain while the clock ticked on the wash stand
and the moon soaked with wet light his tangled clothes upon the floor.
Each night he added to the pattern of his fancies until drowsiness closed down
upon some vivid scene with an oblivious embrace.
For a while these reveries provided an outlet for his imagination; they were a
satisfactory hint of the unreality of reality, a promise that the rock of the
world was founded securely on a fairy’s wing.
An instinct toward his future glory had led him, some months before, to the small
Lutheran College of Saint Olaf in southern Minnesota.
He stayed there two weeks, dismayed at its ferocious indifference to the drums
of his destiny, to destiny itself, and despising the janitor’s work with
which he was to pay his way through. Then he drifted back to Lake Superior, and he
was still searching for something to do on that day that Dan Cody’s yacht
dropped anchor in the shallows along Shore Cody was 50 years old then, a product of
the Nevada silver fields, of the Yukon, of every rush for metal since 75. The
transactions in Montana copper that made him many times a millionaire found him
physically robust but on the verge of soft-mindedness, and, suspecting this, an infinite number
of women tried to separate him from his money. The none too Savory ramifications
by which Ella k the newspaper woman, played Madame de maintenance to his
weakness and sent him to sea in a yacht where common knowledge to the turgid
sub-journalism of 1902. He had been coasting along all two hospitable shores
for five years when he turned up as James Gatz’s destiny at Little girl's point
the young Gods resting on his oars and looking up at the rail deck The yacht
represented all the beauty and glamor in the world.
I suppose he smiled at Cody— —he had probably discovered that people liked him when he smiled.
At any rate Cody asked him a few questions (one of them elicited the brand
new name) and found that he was quick and extravagantly ambitious.
A few days later he took him to Duluth and bought him a blue coat, six pair of
white duck trousers, and a yachting cap.
And when the ptolemae left for the West Indies and the Barbary Coast, Gatsby left too.
He was employed in a vague personal capacity— —while he remained with Cody he
was in turn steward, mate, skipper, secretary, and even Jailer for Dan Cody
sober knew what lavish doings Dan Cody drunk might soon be about, and he
provided for such contingencies by reposing more and more trust in Gatsby.
The arrangement lasted five years, during which the boat went three times around
the Continent. It might have lasted indefinitely except for the fact that
Ella Kay came on board one night in Boston and a week later Dan Cody inhospitably died.
I remember the portrait of him up in Gatsby’s bedroom, a gray floored man with
a hard, empty face— —the pioneered debauche who during one phase of American life
brought back to the Eastern seaboard the savage violence of the frontier brothel and saloon.
It was indirectly due to Cody that Gatsby drank so little.
Sometimes in the course of gay parties women used to rub champagne into his
hair; for himself he formed the habit of letting liquor alone.
And it was from Cody that he inherited money— —a legacy of twenty five thousand dollars.
He didn’t get it. He never understood the legal device that was used against him,
but what remained of the millions went intact to elake He was left with his singularly
appropriate education; the vague contour of Jay Gatsby had filled out to the
substantiality of a man.
He told me all of this very much later,
but I’ve put it down here with the idea of exploding those first wild rumors
about his antecedents, which weren’t even faintly true.
Moreover he told it to me at a time of confusion, when I had reached the point
of believing everything and nothing about him.
So I take advantage of this short halt, while Gatsby, so to speak, caught his
breath, to clear this set of misconceptions away.
It was a halt, too, in my association with his affairs.
For several weeks I didn’t see him or hear his voice on the phone—
—mostly I was in New York, trotting around with Jordan and trying to ingratiate
myself with her senile aunt— —but finally I went over to his house one Sunday afternoon.
I hadn’t been there two minutes when somebody brought Tom Buchanan in for a drink.
I was startled, naturally, but the really surprising thing was that it hadn’t happened before.
They were a party of three on horseback— —Tom and a man named Sloan and a pretty
woman in a brown riding habit who had been there previously.
“I’m delighted to see you,” said Gatsby, standing on his porch. “I’m delighted that
you dropped in.” As though they cared!
“Sit right down. Have a cigarette or a cigar.” He walked around the room quickly,
ringing bells. “I’ll have something to drink for you in just a minute.”
He was profoundly affected by the fact that Tom was there.
But he would be uneasy anyhow until he had given them something, realizing in a
vague way that that was all they came for.
Mr Sloan wanted nothing.
A lemonade? No, thanks. A little champagne no Nothing at all, thanks… I’m sorry—
“Did you have a nice ride?” “Very good roads around here.” “I suppose the automobiles—” “Yeah.”
Moved by an irresistible impulse, Gatsby turned to Tom, who had accepted the
introduction as a stranger.
“I believe we’ve met somewhere before, Mr.
Buchanan.” “Oh, yes,” said Tom graphically polite, but obviously not remembering. “So
we did. I remember very well.” “About two weeks ago.” “That’s right.
You were with Nick here.” “I know your wife,” continued Gatsby, almost aggressively that's so?”
Tom turned to me.
“You live here, Nick?” “Next door that's so?” Mr. Sloane didn’t enter into the
conversation, but lounged back hardly in his chair; the women said nothing either—
—until unexpectedly, after two high balls she became cordial.
“We’ll all come over to your next party, Mr. Gatsby,” she suggested. “What do you say?”
“Certainly; I’d be delighted to have you.” “Be very nice,”
said Mr Sloan without gratitude. “Well thank god to be starting home.”
“Please don’t hurry,” Gatsby urged them. He had control of himself now, and he wanted
to see more of Tom.
“Why don’t you— —why don’t you stay for supper? I wouldn’t be surprised if some
other people dropped in from New York.” “You come to supper with me said the lady
enthusiastically. “Both of you.” This included me.
Mr Sloan got to his feet. “Come along,” he said— —but to her only. “I mean it,” she
insisted. “I’d love to have you. Lots of room.” Gatsby looked at me questioningly.
He wanted to go and he didn’t see that Mr Sloan had determined he shouldn’t.
“I’m afraid I won’t be able to,” I said will you come,” she urged, concentrating on
Gatsby.
Mr Sloan murmured something close to her ear.
“We won’t be late if we start now,” she insisted aloud.
“I haven’t got a horse,” said Gatsby. “I used
to ride in the army, but I’ve never bought a horse. I’ll have to follow you
in my car. Excuse me for just a minute.” The rest of us walked out into the porch,
where Sloane and the lady began an impassioned conversation aside.
“My God, I believe the man’s coming,” said
Tom. “Doesn’t he know she doesn’t want him?”
“She says she does want him.” “She has a big
dinner party and he won’t know his soul there.” He frowned. “I wonder where in the devil
he met Daisy. By God, I may be old-fashioned in my ideas, but women run
around too much these days to suit me.
They meet all kinds of crazy fish.” Suddenly Mr Sloan and the lady walked
down the steps and mounted their horses.
“Come on,” said Mr Sloan to Tom, “we’re late.
We’ve gotta go.” And then to me: “Tell him we couldn’t wait, will you?”
Tom and I shook hands, the rest of us exchanged a cool nod, and they trotted
quickly down the drive, disappearing under the August foliage just as Gatsby,
with hat and light overcoat in hand, came out the front door.
Tom was evidently perturbed at daisies running around alone, for on the
following Saturday night he came with her to Gatsby’s party.
Perhaps his presence gave the evening its peculiar quality of oppressiveness—
—it stands out in my memory from Gatsby’s other parties that summer
they were the same people, or at least the same sort of people, the same
profusion of champagne, the same many colored many keyed commotion,
but I felt an unpleasantness in the air, a pervading harshness that hadn’t been there before
It is invariably saddening to look through new eyes at things upon which
you have expended your own powers of adjustment.
They arrived at twilight, and, as we strolled out among the sparkling
hundreds, Daisy’s voice was playing murmurous tricks in her throat. “These
things excite me so she whispered.
“If you want to kiss me anytime during the evening, Nick, just let me know and
I’ll be glad to arrange it for you. Just mention my name. Or present a green card.
I’m giving out green—” “Look around,” suggested Gatsby.
“I’m looking around. I’m having a marvelous You must see the faces of many
people you’ve heard about.” Tom’s arrogant eyes roamed the crowd.
“We don’t go around very much,” he said; “in fact, I was just I don’t know
a soul here.” “Perhaps you know that lady.” Gatsby indicated a gorgeous, scarcely
human orchid of a woman who sat in state under a white plum tree.
Tom and Daisy stared, with that peculiar unreal feeling that accompanies the
recognition of a hitherto ghostly celebrity of the movies.
“She’s lovely,” said Daisy.
“The man bending over her is her director.” He took them ceremoniously from group to
group: “Mrs. Buchanan… and Mr. Buchanan—” After an instant hesitation he added: “the polo
player Ono objected Tom quickly, “not me.” But evidently the sound of it pleased
Gatsby for Tom remained “the polo player” for the rest of the evening.
“I’ve never met so many celebrities,” Daisy exclaimed. “I liked that man— —what was his
name?— ?—with the sort of blue nose.” Gatsby identified him, adding that he was
a small producer. “Well, I liked him anyhow.” “I’d a little rather not be the polo
player,” said Tom pleasantly, “I’d rather look at all these famous people in— —in oblivion.”
Daisy and Gatsby danced. I remember being surprised by his graceful, conservative
foxtrot— —I had never seen him dance before.
Then they sauntered over to my house and sat on the steps for half an hour, while
at her request I remained watchfully in the garden. “In case there’s a fire or a
flood,” she explained, “or any act of God.” Tom appeared from his oblivion as we
were sitting down to supper together.
“Do you mind if I eat with some people over here?” he said. “A fellow is getting
off some funny stuff.” “Go ahead answer Daisy genially, “and if you want to take down any
addresses here’s my little gold pencil.”… She looked around after a moment and
told me the girl was “common but pretty,” and I knew that except for the half hour
she’d been alone with Gatsby she wasn’t having a good time.
We were at a particularly tipsy table.
That was my fault— —Gatsby had been called to the phone, and I’d enjoyed these same
people only two weeks before. But what it amused me then turned septic on the air
now. “How do you feel, Miss bedecker The girl addressed was trying, unsuccessfully,
to slump against my shoulder. At this inquiry she sat up and opened her eyes why
A massive and lethargic woman, who had been urging Daisy to play golf with her
at the local club tomorrow, spoke in Miss bedecker's defense Oh, she’s all right
now. When she’s had five or six cocktails she always starts screaming like that. I
tell her she ought to leave it alone.” “I do leave it alone,” affirmed the accused hollowly.
“We heard you yelling, so I said to docs of it here: ‘There’s somebody that needs
your help, Doc.’ “She’s much obliged, I’m sure,” said another friend, without
gratitude, “but you got her dress all wet when you stuck her head in the pool.”
“Anything I hate is to get my head stuck in a pool,” mumbled Miss bedecker They
almost drowned me once over in New Jersey.” “Then you want to leave it alone counter Dr Civet.
“Speak for yourself!” cried Mr Decker violently. “Your hand shakes. I wouldn’t
let you operate on me!” It was like that. Almost the last thing I
remember was standing with Daisy and watching the moving picture director and
his Star. They were still under the White Plum tree and their faces were touching
except for a pale, thin ray of moonlight between.
It occurred to me that he had been very slowly bending toward her all evening to
attain this proximity, and even while I watched I saw him stoop
one ultimate degree in kiss at her cheek.
“I like her,” said Daisy, “I think she’s lovely.” But the rest offended her— —and then
arguably because it wasn’t a gesture but an emotion.
She was appalled by West Egg, this unprecedented “place” that Broadway had
begotten upon a Long Island fishing village— —appalled by its raw Vigor that chafed
under the old euphemisms and by the two obtrusive fate that herded its
inhabitants along a shortcut from nothing to nothing.
She saw something awful in the very simplicity she failed to understand.
I sat on the front steps with them while they waited for their car.
It was dark here in front; only the bright door sent 10 square feet of light
volleying out into the soft black morning I sat on the front steps with them while
they waited for their car it was dark here in front only the bright door sent
10 square feet of light volleying out into the soft black morning.
Sometimes a shadow moved against a dressing room blind above, gave way to
another shadow, an indefinite procession of shadows, who rouged and powdered in an
invisible glass. “Who is Gatsby anyhow?” demanded Tom suddenly. “Some big bootlegger?”
“Where’d you hear that?” I inquired. “I didn’t hear it. I imagined it. A lot of
these newly rich people are just big bootleggers, you know.” “Not Gatsby,” I said shortly.
He was silent for a moment. The pebbles of the drive crunched under his feet.
“Well, he certainly must have strained himself to get this menagerie together.”
A breeze stirred at the gray haze of daisies for a collar. “At least they're
more interesting than people we know,” she said with an effort. “You didn’t look so interested.”
“Well, I was.” Tom laughed and turned to me.
“Did you notice Daisy’s face when that girl asked her to put her under a cold shower?”
Daisy began to sing with the music in a husky, rhythmic whisper,
bringing out a meaning in each word that it had never had before and would never have again.
When the melody rose her voice broke up sweetly, following it, in a way contra
alto voices have, and each change tipped out a little of her warm human magic upon the air.
“Lots of people come who haven’t been invited,” she said suddenly. “That girl
hadn’t been invited. They simply forced their way in and he’s too polite to object.”
“I’d like to know who he is and what he does,” insisted Tom.
“And I think I’ll make a point of finding out.”
“I can tell you right now,” she answered. “He owned some drug stores a lot of drug
stores He built them up himself.” The dilatory limousine came rolling up the drive.
“Good night, Nick,” said Daisy.
Her glance left me and sought the lighted top of the steps, where “Three
O’Clock in the Morning,” a neat, sad little waltz of the year, was
drifting out the open door.
After all, in the very casualness of Gatsby’s party they were romantic
possibilities totally absent from her world.
What was it up there in the song that seemed to be calling her back inside?
What would happen now in the dim in calculable hours?
Perhaps some unbelievable guest would arrive, a person infinitely rare and to
be marveled at, some authentically radiant young girl who with one fresh
glance at Gatsby, one moment of magical encounter, would blot out those five
years of unwavering devotion.
I stayed late that night. Gatsby asked me to wait until he was free, and I lingered
in the garden until the inevitable swimming party had run up, chilled and
exalted, from the black beach, until the lights were extinguished in the guest rooms overhead.
When he came down the steps at last the tanned skin was drawn unusually tight on
his face, and his eyes were bright and tired.
“She didn’t like it,” he said immediately.
“Of course she did.” “She didn’t like it,” he insisted. “She didn’t have a good time.”
He was silent, and I guessed that his unutterable depression.
“I feel far away from her,” he said. “It’s hard to make her understand.”
“You mean about the dance?” “The dance?” He dismissed all the dances he had given
with a snap of his fingers. “Old sport, the dance is unimportant.”
He wanted nothing less of Daisy than that she should go to Tom and say: “I
never loved you.” After she had obliterated four years with that
sentence they could decide upon the more practical measures to be taken.
One of them was that, after she was free, they were to go back to Louisville and
be married from her house— —just as if it were five years ago.
“And she doesn’t understand,” he said. “She used to be able to understand. We’d sit
for hours—” He broke off and began to walk up and
down a desolate path of fruit rinds and discarded favors and crushed flowers.
“I wouldn’t ask too much of her,” I ventured. “You can’t repeat the past.” “Can’t
repeat the past?” he cried incredulously. “Why of course you can!”
He looked around him wildly, as if the past were lurking here in the shadows of
his house, just out of reach of his hand.
“I’m going to fix everything just the way it was before,” he said, nodding
determinedly. “She’ll see.” He talked a lot about the past, and I
gathered that he wanted to recover something, some idea of himself perhaps,
that had gone into loving Daisy. His life had been confused and disordered since
then, but if he could once return to a certain starting place and go over it
all slowly, he could find out what that thing was… One autumn night, five years before, they
had been walking down the street when the leaves were falling, and they came to
a place where there were no trees and the sidewalk was white with moonlight.
They stopped here and turned toward each other. Now it was a cool night with that
mysterious excitement in it which comes the two changes of the year.
The quiet lights in the houses were humming out in the darkness
and there was a stir and bustle among the stars.
Out of the corner of his eye Gatsby saw that the blocks of the sidewalk really
formed a ladder and mounted to a secret place above the trees— —he could climb to it,
if he climbed alone, and once there he could suck on the path of life,
gulp down the incomparable milk of wonder.
His heart beat faster and faster as Daisy’s white face came up to his own.
He knew that when he kissed this girl, and forever when his unhuderable visions
to her perishable breath, his mind would never romp again like the mind of God.
So he waited, listening for a moment longer to the tuning fork that had been struck upon a
star.
Then he kissed her.
At his lips’ touch she blossomed for him like a flower and the incarnation was complete.
Through all he said, even through his appalling sentimentality, I was reminded of something—
—an elusive rhythm, a fragment of lost words, that I had heard somewhere a long time ago.
For a moment a phrase tried to take shape in my mouth and my lips parted
like a dumb man’s, as though there was more struggling upon them than a wisp of
startled air. But they made no sound, and what I had almost remembered was uncommunicable
forever